Guide to the Ezra Lahad Yiddish & Hebrew theater: ephemera, 1936-1974
Department of Special Collections
Ezra Lahad Yiddish & Hebrew theater: ephemera,
1936-1974
M1133
Lahad, Ezra, 1918-1995
2 linear ft. (4 manuscript boxes)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Yiddish and other theater ephemera including Purim plays, a program aabout Ida Kaminska and the Jewish State Theatre of Poland, and programs for the Fourth Theatre Festival of Moscow-Leningrad, 1936.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Acquisition Information
Received by the library, 1998.
Biography
Ezra Lahad (1918-1995) was born in Minsk, attended a Yiddish-language gymnasium in Vilna (Vilnieus), and emigrated to Palestine in 1935. From 1948 to 1961 he served in the Israeli Defense Forces, in military procurement and ammunitions. His last position in the IDF was editor of the bulletin of the Israeli fleet, "Be-ma'arkhot yam." Subsequently, in civilian life, he edited a publication issued by the municipality of Haifa, "Hefah 'ovedet." Upon retirement he served as a volunteer at the Ghetto Fighters' House, a Holocaust museum and archive located in a kibbutz in northern Israel that was established by Holocaust survivors.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
Yiddish and other theater ephemera including Purim plays, a program aabout Ida Kaminska and the Jewish State Theatre of Poland, and programs for the Fourth Theatre Festival of Moscow-Leningrad, 1936.
Access Terms
Kaminska, Ida.; Jewish State Theatre of Poland.; Fourth Theatre Festival Moscow-Leningrad (1936 Sept. 1-10); Jewish theater.; Theater, Yiddish.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Newspaper clippings
  - Yiddish plays 1925 - 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Yiddish plays 1940 - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Yiddish plays 1948 - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Yiddish plays1961 - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Ha-bimah" Theater (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Ha-ohel" Theater (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Advertisements for plays (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Theater criticism (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Literary criticism (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Literary essays (in Yiddish) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Yiddish poetry (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Translated poetry (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Jewish authors in Russia (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Kushnirov, Bergelson, Peper, Halkin, Markish, and more.
  - Yiddish actors (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Elisheva. An article by Max RaisinFebruary 1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    The tragic mystery of a convert who became noted poet in Israel.
    Bychovsky, Elishva; Raisin, Max
  - Goldfaden Avraham (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Uri Zvi Grinberg (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Itsik Manger (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Peretz Markish, fiction and poetry (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Zeitlin Shneur Zalman (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Yehoshua SobolFebruary 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    An article from "Yediot Aharonot". A famous Israeli playwright writes his first Yiddish play.
  - Literary criticism (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Literary essays in Yiddish (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Poetry (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Saturday supplement, Yediot Ahronot. August 7, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Supplement, Israel's 25th anniversary, Maariv. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Supplement, Israel's 25th anniversary, Maariv. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Supplement, Israel's 25th anniversary, Yediot Ahronot. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Supplement, Israel's 25th anniversary, Yediot Ahronot. 1973 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Theater criticism (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Yiddish plays, 1925-1938 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Series 2. Programs of plays and concerts
  - Subseries 1. Haifa Municipal Theater
    - Original Plays 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Original Plays 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Original Plays 1981-1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Translated Plays 1971-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Translated Plays 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Programs of plays: Haifa Municipal Theater, 1961-1967 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Programs of plays: Haifa Municipal Theater, 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Programs of plays: Haifa Municipal Theater, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Programs of plays: Haifa Municipal Theater, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Programs of plays: Haifa Municipal Theater, 1971-1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 2. Other theaters in Israel
    - "Ha-bimah" theater [1 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - "Ha-ohel" theater1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - "Ha-martef" theater (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - "Ha-bimah" theater [2 of 2] (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3. Theaters outside of Israel
    - Theatro del Colle Oppio: Settemmezzo/ Alfredo Polacci1952 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Moscow, Leningrad, Kharkov, Tiflis1936 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      12 programs from the Fourth Theater Festival Moscow-Leningrad, September 1-10, 1936
    - Mermaid Theater, LondonJuly 1974 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Cole, an entertainment based on the words and music of Cole Porter
  - Subseries 4. Music
    - Ashmedai, opera in two acts1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Various programs 1971 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Viennese Evening at the Royal Albert HallSeptember 29, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Series 3. Off-prints
  - Lurya, Shalom (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Shmeruk, Chone (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Three Plays (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Pinski, David; Gorali, Mosheh on Tireni Matityah Nisim; Resler, Binyamin
  - Americana Germanica: Popular poetry of the Russian Jews1898 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Leo Wiener
  - Theater-related papers in English, Hebrew and Yiddish (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Yaari Avraham; Gordin Jacob; Goldfaden Avraham; Almagor Dan
  - Miscellaneous papers on linguistics, Zionism, and more. (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Series 4. Printouts of plays and manuscripts
  - Plays in Hebrew1912-1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Perez, Y.L; Shneur, Zalman; Shalom, Sh.; Bar-Yosef, Yehoshua
  - Plays in Yiddish,n.d. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manuscript: Nibe ni meni kukuriku, by Itsik Shwartz (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscript: Nevokhadnetser's mishpet, by N.B Bazilinske (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Based on a theme by Ludwig Philippson (1811-1889)
  - Manuscript and music for Hershele Ostropoler, by Gershnzon1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Play: Ish ha-agadah, by Yaakov Orland (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Play: ha-Matsod ha-melakhuti shel ha-shemesh, by Peter Shaffer, translated by R. Eliaz (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Play: A Mayseh mit Hershele Ostropoler, by Mosheh Lifshits (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Play: A Mayseh mit Hershele Ostropoler, by Mosheh Lifshits, photocopy (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Play: Menahem Mendel baal ha-haloymes (Sholem Aleichem), by A. Ashman (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Play: Meshartam shel shene adonim, by Karlo Golodni/Yosef Milo (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Play: Meshiah, by Martin Sherman, translated by Navah Semel (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Play: Metsukah u-tekumah, by Yosef Oren (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Play: ha-Mirpeset (Jean Genet), by Mati Meged. 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Play: Motek at yodaat she-ani... by Robert Anderson, Hebrew by Edna Shavit (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Play: ha-Protocol shel asir tsiyon, by Adah Amikol (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Play: Pesha tsevai [by Moshe Shamir?] (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Play: ha-Rasha baal onsho, by Zeev Vardi (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Play: ha-Shiur, by Eugene Ionesco (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Play: Snif be-Eilat, satirah, by Nahum Benari (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Play: [Unidentified, Hebrew, 96 p.; p. 1-58] (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Play: [Unidentified, Hebrew, 96 p.; p. 59-96] (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Play: [Unidentified, Hebrew, 52 p. ] (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Play: Yaakov Frank, by M. Kolbak (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Play: Yaakov ve-Rahel, by A. Shlonski (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Play: Di Zug fargeyt nit, by Itsik Fefer. Photocopy (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Play: Melukhat Shaul, by Josef Triplowitz. Handwritten, 1796 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Series 5. Correspondence and notes
  - Incoming mail to Lahad Ezra and family (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Ezra Lahad's outgoing mail (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Announcements and invitations (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - A letter to the Ghetto Fighters Museum1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    This letter was written by Kremerman Yehezkel. It includes his memories from the Vilna ghetto.
  - Bibliographical work (Box 3, Folder 14)
    This folder contains Rose Shoshana's appeal in the newspaper and the resulting correspondence.
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Incoming mail to Ezra Lahad and family (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ezra Lahad's outgoing mail (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Series 6. Yiddish theater personalities
  - Ida Kaminska and the Jewish State Theatre of Poland1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photoprints (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Avraham Morewski (Box 4, Folder 4)
    The folder contains a portfolio of his roles in a postcard format.
  - Clippings of caricatures and cartoons (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Photo reproductions (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series 7. Ezra Lahad's work
  - Manuscripts (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Offprints and newspaper clippings (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Bibliographical work (Box 4, Folder 9)
    This folder contains a copy of a bibliographical work by Yaari Avraham, titled Ha-Mahazeh Ha-ivri, with many notes added by Ezra Lahad.
  - Bibliographical work - miscellaneous papers (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bibliographical work: miscellaneous papers (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Essays (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Series 8. Theaters in Europe
  - Goset State Yiddish Theater in Moscow (Box 4, Folder 11)
    This folder contains a printout with the history of the theater and pictures of actors and scenes.
  - Kamer-teater, Moscow (Box 4, Folder 12)
    The folder contains programs and bewspaper clippings.
  - Wroclaw Jewish Theatre (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Series 9. Personal
  - Immigration certificate1934 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    This folder contains the immigration certificate from the Government of Palestine to Ezra Lahad's family (Parents and sister) allowing the family to enter Palestine.
  - Muli Lahad, Ezra Lahad's son (Box 4, Folder 15)
    This folder contains newspaper clippings concerning Muli Lahad. One is a story about an accident he had with his family, and the other is an interview with him, as a psychologist working in a crisis center in Northern Israel, about dealing with crisis.
- Series 10. Audiovisual materials
  - Interview in the Israeli radio, 1 audiocassette (Othertype 1)
    This is a recording (cassette) of an interview with Ezra Lahad in the Israeli radio
- Series 11. Miscellaneous
  - Various publications of the Haifa Municipal Theater (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Various publications of the "Ha-bimah" Theater (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - The early days of the Israeli theater (Box 4, Folder 18)
    This folder contains correspondence and programs.
  - Drawings of costumes and set designs (Box 4, Folder 19)
    This folder contains original drawings of an unknown artist.
  - Ex Libris plates and date book (Box 4, Folder 20)
    this folder contais Lahad's collection of Ex Libris plates.
  - Various fragments of publications (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - WW2-related materials (Box 4, Folder 22)
    This folder includes a letter from Watsow Ghetto, an interview with Mosheh Kraus.
  - Miscellaneous photos (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets (Box 4, Folder 24)
    This folder contains pamphlets about Tel Aviv, the Common Market, and more.
  - Lahad family documents (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Announcements and invitations (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Fragments of published material (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Meeting minutes (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Notes (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Photocopies (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Photocopies: Frontispieces (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Photocopies: Literary works (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Photocopies: Literary works (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Photocopies: Newspaper and journal articles (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Photographs (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Poetry (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Poster and 3 handbills (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Publication announcement: Encyclopaedia Judaica, Keter Publishing, 1971 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Publication announcement: Facsimile editions of Hebrew munuscripts, Makor Publishing, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [materials pertaining to] Sister Rosa Wollstein (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - A Traveling Jewish Theater, newsletters and informational materials, ca. 1981 (Box 8, Folder 12)